Guide to the Gerald L. Pearson Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Gerald L. Pearson papers
1934-1987
SC0350
Pearson, Gerald L., 1905-1987.
6.5 Linear feet
Correspondence, 1961-1982, research notebooks on optical properties of solids and other subjects, technical reports prepared during his tenure at Bell Telephone Laboratories, reprints, photographs and slides, legal papers relating to patents, transcript of an oral history interview, memorabilia, and other miscellaneous items.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Mildred Pearson, 1988 and 1992, and James Harris, 1989.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Professor of Electrical Engineering at Stanford University from 1960 to 1987 and Director of Stanford Solid State Electronics Laboratory. Research Physicist at Bell Telephone Laboratories from 1929 to 1960 in the field of solid-state electronics. Co-inventor of the solar cell, Pearson held a total of 34 U.S. patents relating to thermistors, transistors, silicon power diodes, and solar cells.
Description of the Collection
Correspondence, 1961-1982, research notebooks on optical properties of solids and other subjects, technical reports prepared during his tenure at Bell Telephone Laboratories, reprints, photographs and slides, legal papers relating to patents, transcript of an oral history interview, memorabilia, and other miscellaneous items.
The correspondence, dating from 1960 through 1981, consists of letters sent and received while Pearson was a professor of Electrial Engineering at Stanford university. Also included are technical reports for Bell Telephone Labs, reprints, articles and lectures concerning the solar cell, photographs and slides documenting the solar cell, a notebook containing abstracts of papers Pearson presented to the American Physical Society, affidavits and testimony relating to patent trials and four transistor artifacts.
Access Terms
Bell Telephone Laboratories.; Harris, James; Pearson, Gerald L., 1905-1987.; Stanford University. Department of Electrical Engineering. Faculty.; Stanford University. Solid State Electronics Laboratory.; Electrical engineering; Physicists.; Solar cells.
Collection Contents
- Original Accession
  - Correspondence
    incoming & outgoing arranged alphabetically
    - 9/60-6/61 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 7/61-2/62 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 4/62-4-63 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 4/63-2/64 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 3/64-12/64 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1/65-12/65 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 10/65-11/66 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1/67-12/14/67 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1/68-12/68 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 1969 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - 1970 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - 1971 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - 1972 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - 1973 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - 1974 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - 1975 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - 1976 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - 1977 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - 1978 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - 1979 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - 1980 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - [James F.] Gibbons (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - [James F.] Gibbons (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Solid State Electronics in the USSR Report on a lecture tour in the Soviet Union, 9/17-10/16 1971 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Solar Cells: technical reports, newspaper clippings and photographs (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Research notebook (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Pearson technical reports (Bell Telephone Labs) and articles (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Pearson technical reports (Bell Telephone Labs) (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Pearson reprints, articles and papers presented (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - reprints, technical reports (authors other than Pearson) (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - technical reports (Bell Telephone Labs and authors other than Pearson) (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - technical reports (Bell Telephone Labs and authors other than Pearson) (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Pearson reprints and technical reports (Bell Telephone Labs, and authors other than Pearson) (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - reprints and articles (authors other than Pearson) (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - articles (authors other than Pearson) (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Pearson article and accompanying photographs (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Pearson essay (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Pearson article and accompanying photographs and negatives (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Course Description and teaching materials for EE-257, Experimental Solid State Electronics (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Lists of Pearson's: Technical Publications, Publications and U. S. Patents by Pearson assigned to Bell Telephone Laboratories (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Awards, memberships in national/ international societies (Box 4, Folder 20-23)
  - Ephemera: Naval certified citizen Employee Identification, Membership card for the Franklin Institute and rate of pay card (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Photographs/negatives: Explorer VI, solar-powered satelite, circa August 7, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Photographs/negatives: portraits of Gerald Pearson in laboratory (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Photographs/negatives: laborato:ry equipment, graphs and charts (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Photographs: solar batteries, crystals, silicon power rectifiers, graphs, charts and diagrams (press releases, articles and tec1mical reports accompany same photographs) (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - volume containing abstracts of papers Pearson presented to the American Physical Society, 1928-1978 (Box 5)
  - transcript of Gerald L. Pearson's testimony; Sper:ry-Rand Corporation vs. Bernard J. Rothlein, et aI, 2/18/64 (Box 5)
  - affidavits for Gerald L. Pearson in patent cases: -Jack st. Clair vs. Robert N. Noyce -Fairchild camera vs. Texas Instruments (Box 5)
  - glass slides (approximately 100): charts and diagrams (Box 5)
  - 35 mm slides (approximately 450): charts and diagrams (student research ?) (Box 5)
  - artifacts: three [silicon power rectifiers] (Box 5)
  - Affidavit of Gerald L. Pearson, in the German Patent Office, re: Application of Fairchild camera and Instrument Corporation No. 1,197,548; Filed: April 26, 1960; Semiconductor Device With One or More PN Junctions and Methcxi to Prcxiuce Them (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - The Transistor and Related Experiments, by J. Bardeen, W.H. Brattain, W. Shockley, G.L. Pearson; Bell Telephone System, Technical Publication, Monograph B-1574 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Photographs, 5 black and white photographs (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - EE 257 Experiments I to VII (inactive) (Box 6, Folder 4)
    I Conducti vi ty and Hall Effect of Gennanium; II Drift Mobility, Diffusion Length and Lifetime of Holes in Germanium; III Recording Spectometer and its Use in Measuring the Absorption Edge in Silicon Crystals; IV Dielectric Constant Experiment; V Specific Heat Experiment; VI Ferrmagnetic Resonance Experiment; VII Nuclear Magnetic Resonance
  - Alfried Krupp von Bohlen and Halbach Energy Research Prize, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    List of Recipients, Addresses, Pearson's address
  - Laboratory Notebook: Optical Properties of Solids, circa 1954-1957 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Oral History/Biographical Sketch (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Study of the History of Solid State Physics Correspondence/Memos, circa 1979 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Miscellany (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Additional Material, Accesion ARCH-1992-135
  - Sperry Rand Corporation v. Bernard J. Rothlein, et. al - legal papers, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photographs of Pearson, W. Shockley, and solar cells (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Solar cells: reprints, technical reports, clipping, 1954-55 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Transistor: Bell Labs press release and reports re: first demonstration, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bell Laboratories RECORD (3 issues) and BUSINESS WEEK, 1960 Mar 26 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - F.J. Biondi, ed., TRANSISTOR TECHNOLOGY, vol. 2 (Box 1)
  - Examples of solar cells (Box 1)